<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on meiji163</title>
    <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on meiji163</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://meiji163.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial Hyperbolic Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/combo-hyperbolic-embedding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://meiji163.github.io/post/combo-hyperbolic-embedding/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The manifold hypothesis says that most real-world datasets lie approximately on a low-dimensional manifold, but by some Kantian twist of fate we rarely have direct access to this manifold1. As a result, most machine learning techniques utilize only local structure (e.g. the &amp;ldquo;loss + SGD&amp;rdquo; machine).
In contrast, Topological and Geometric Data Analysis (TGDA) is a burgeoning field that studies the global structure of data. This is exciting not only because of potential domain applications &amp;ndash; it also opens possibilities for porting a lot of powerful and beautiful math to the ML realm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun With GitHub CLI Extensions</title>
      <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/gh-extension/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://meiji163.github.io/post/gh-extension/</guid>
      <description>And everything else which can be attributed to body presupposes extension, and is only a mode of that which is extended.
&amp;ndash; Descartes, Principles of Philosophy
 Introduction gh is the official GitHub CLI, maintained in the public cli/cli repository.
Like its predecessor hub1, gh wraps common git commands. But gh does much more, ultimately aiming to be a general GitHub interface for your terminal. You can for example run actions with gh workflow, publish gists with gh gist, or access your codespaces with gh cs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context Tree Weighting and Compression</title>
      <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/context-tree-weighting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://meiji163.github.io/post/context-tree-weighting/</guid>
      <description>In this post I go over the basics of data compression with arithmetic coding and describe the Context Tree Weighting algorithm. At the end I discuss implementation and some experimental results.
Information Theory Review First a quick review of information theory. Suppose that we receive some data \(x\) drawn from a discrete random variable \(X\), whose probability distribution is \(P\). Then the Shannon information content of \(x\) is defined as</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast Sum of Two Squares Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/sum-of-squares/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://meiji163.github.io/post/sum-of-squares/</guid>
      <description>In this post I show how writing primes as the sum of two squares is related to factoring Gaussian integers. I then describe an algorithm to compute the sum of two squares representation.
Gaussian Integers I have a special penchant for Gaussian integers because they are the first ring I learned about (besides the regular integers of course). Mathematically, they are the set of complex numbers \(a+bi\) with \(a,b\) integers, and they are denoted as \(\mathbb{Z}[i]\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liouville&#39;s Theorem on Conformal Rigidity</title>
      <link>https://meiji163.github.io/post/conformal-rigidity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://meiji163.github.io/post/conformal-rigidity/</guid>
      <description>In this post I summarize the content and proof of Liouville&amp;rsquo;s Theorem on Conformal Rigidity, which I learned in 2018 from Professor Alex Austin (now at RIT) in his class at UCLA.
Conformal Maps A conformal transformation is one that preserves angles. In two dimensions, this is equivalent to being holomorphic and having a non-vanishing derivative. There are tons of these transformations (my personal favorites are Mobius transformations). In fact, the famous Riemann mapping Theorem asserts that any simply connected domain \( U \subset \mathbb{C} \) admits a bijective conformal map \(f: U \to \mathbb{D}\) to the unit disc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
